Have you ever asked, “How long?”
「エホバ いつまでですか」
If you’re enduring
そう尋ねずにはいられなかったことが
あるかもしれません
some challenging circumstance right now
—perhaps old age, a serious illness,
高齢や重い病気や
他の難しい問題のために
or some other pressure—
such a question is very understandable.
そう尋ねたくなるのも無理はありません
Or perhaps you’re in the position
of giving assistance
あるいはあなたは とても難しい状況に
置かれている家族や
and trying to encourage a family member
or someone in the congregation
会衆の仲間を援助していて
who’s going through
a very difficult time right now,
力になりたいと思っているかもしれません
and perhaps you’ve wondered
about the same question: ‘How long?
そしてやはり こう尋ねたくなります
「エホバ 私たちはいつまで
忍耐しなければいけないのですか」
How long do we all
have to endure all of this?’
こういう質問をしたのは
ハバククだけではありません
Asking that question puts us in good company.
To cite one example, at Psalm 13:1, 2,
例えば 詩編 13:1, 2で
King David asked the question, “How long?”
ダビデ王は 矢継ぎ早に4回
「いつまで」と尋ねています
four times in quick succession.
こうあります 「エホバ いつまで私を
忘れているのですか 永遠にですか
Maybe you recall: “How long, O Jehovah,
will you forget me?
“Forever?
“How long will you hide your face from me?
いつまで顔を隠すのですか
いつまで私は思い悩み 毎日悲しみに
暮れなければならないのですか
“How long will I have anxious concern,
“with grief in my heart each day?
How long will my enemy triumph over me?”
いつまで敵は勝利するのですか」
David was a human—a real person
ダビデは私たちと同じような
感情を持つ人間でした
with real problems and real feelings.
さまざまな問題も抱えていました
ハバククも私たちと同じように
弱さを持つ人間でした
Habakkuk was another human just like us
who was plagued with questions,
そして「いつまでですか」と尋ねました
and he asked the same: “How long?”
エホバがハバククに
どう答えたかを考えると
How Jehovah responded to Habakkuk
can strengthen our resolve to wait
私たちも もう少しエホバを待とう
just a little while longer
辛抱強く待とうという決意が強まります
on Jehovah, to wait patiently.
Please open your Bible with me
ご一緒にハバクク 1章を開いて
to Habakkuk chapter 1,
and let’s read verses 2 and 3.
2, 3節を読んでみましょう
And notice the succession
ハバククは次から次へと質問をして
of six emotion-filled questions
エホバに切実な気持ちを伝えます
—Habakkuk 1:2, 3:
「エホバ 私はいつまで助けを求めて
叫ばなければならないのですか
“How long, O Jehovah,
あなたは聞いてくださらないのですか
“must I cry for help, but you do not hear?
私はいつまで暴力からの救出を
願わなければならないのですか
“How long must I ask for help from violence,
あなたは介入してくださらないのですか
“but you do not intervene?
私に悪事を見させるのはどうしてですか
“Why do you make me witness wrongdoing?
圧制を見過ごしておられるのは
どうしてですか
“And why do you tolerate oppression?
私の前に破壊や暴力があるのはなぜですか
“Why are destruction and violence before me?
And why do quarreling and conflict abound?”
口論や争いがあまりにも多いのは
なぜですか」
皆さんも同じように感じますか
Do you think those were good questions?
They were.
きっとそうでしょう ハバククは今と
同じように 大変な時に生活していました
Like us, Habakkuk
was living in a very difficult time.
Violence, oppression, injustice were rampant.
暴力や圧制や不正が広く見られていました
ハバククはそうした状況を見たり
経験したりして
Habakkuk was deeply distressed
by the circumstances
that he was experiencing, that he was seeing.
ひどく心を乱されていました
それでハバククは
Naturally, he wanted to know
how long it would be
エホバがいつ約束を果たしてくださるのか
知りたいと思っていました
before Jehovah fulfilled
the promise he had already given
to bring judgment
against that wicked system of things.
悪い人たちを処罰するという約束です
But how Jehovah responded
to his faithful prophet’s questions
では エホバがハバククの質問に
どう答えたかに注目しましょう
really can strengthen
our confidence in Jehovah.
きっとエホバへの信頼が
強まることでしょう
Notice in chapter 2 and verse 3,
ハバクク 2:3をご覧ください
though not obligated to answer,
what did Jehovah tell him?
エホバには答える義務は
ありませんでしたが こう言いました
ハバクク 2:3
Habakkuk 2:3:
“For the vision
is yet for its appointed time,
「この幻は定められた時のためのもので
“and it is rushing toward its end,
終わりに向かって急いでおり
“and it will not lie.
偽りではない
“Even if it should delay,
keep in expectation of it!
たとえ遅れるとしても 待ち続けよ
“For it will without fail come true.
必ずその通りになるからである
It will not be late!”
遅くなることはない！」
A beautiful reassurance from Jehovah,
wouldn’t you agree?
ハバククはこの言葉を聞いて
安心したことでしょう
Analyze those words.
内容を見てみましょう
Notice first that Jehovah assured Habakkuk
まずエホバはハバククに
処罰が必ず下されることを保証しました
that divine judgment was coming.
Jehovah had not changed his stated purpose.
エホバは考えを変えてはいませんでした
And then Jehovah added that there was
「定められた時」に処罰が
下されることを明らかにしました
an “appointed [or fixed] time”
for that judgment.
In effect, Jehovah was telling Habakkuk,
エホバはいわばこう言っていました
‘Habakkuk, the day of judgment
is on my calendar.’
「ハバクク 処罰の日は
私のカレンダーに書いてある」
Jehovah then added more.
さらにこう言いました
He said that the judgment was “rushing
処罰は 「終わり［または実現］に
向かって急いで」いる
toward its end,” or its fulfillment.
「偽りではない」
“It [would] not lie.”
And as a result of thinking and meditating
on those assurances,
ハバククはこのような保証の言葉を
思い巡らしました
Habakkuk had no reason to be impatient
or to give way to despair.
そして諦めたり 絶望したり
すべきではないことを理解しました
In fact, instead of criticizing Habakkuk
このように 切実にエホバに訴え
質問したハバククを
for those very sincere,
very poignant questions,
エホバは批判したりしませんでした
むしろ こう言って励ましました
Jehovah encouraged Habakkuk:
“Keep in expectation of it!”
「待ち続けよ ［心から待ち望め］
Wait eagerly for it.
遅くなることはない」
“It will not be late!”
Well, you know,
it’s one thing to receive encouragement,
励ましの言葉をただ聞くのは
簡単なことです
but I’m sure you’d agree
that it’s another thing to fully accept it,
でもそれを心から受け入れて
自分のものにするのは
to take it to heart and be nourished at heart
by such encouragement.
それほど簡単なことではありません
Did Habakkuk
take Jehovah’s response to heart?
ハバククはどうだったでしょうか
エホバの言葉を受け入れて
力づけられたでしょうか
Did it encourage him?
Well, cast your eyes
to chapter 2 and verse 1,
ハバクク 2:1をご覧ください
and you’ll notice
that Habakkuk’s communication with Jehovah
この聖句にある通り
ハバククはエホバと話すことで
did, in fact, calm his heart.
穏やかな気持ちになることができました
He resolved to keep waiting confidently
ハバククはエホバを信じて
辛抱強く待つことにしました
and patiently on Jehovah.
Later, in chapter 3 and verse 16,
3:16でもハバククは
その決意を言い表しています
Habakkuk repeated his resolve when he said
「私は［エホバ］の日を
静かに待ちます」と言っています
that he would
“quietly wait” for Jehovah’s day.
Well, what does all of this have to do
with you and with me?
では私たちはどうでしょうか
Well, we live at a time when Jehovah
私たちも裁きの日を迎えようとしています
has also appointed a fixed day of judgment.
エホバはその日を定めています
Nearly 2,000 years ago,
エホバは2000年近く前から
the Father already knew
when the end would come, according to Jesus.
この体制を終わらせる時を決めています
At Matthew 24:36,
イエスがマタイ 24:36で
言ったように
what had Jehovah already established?
エホバは「日と時刻」を定めています
A “day and hour.”
So that means that the day
that you and I eagerly anticipate
ですから 私たちが
待ち望んでいるその日は
すでにエホバのカレンダーに
記されています
is on Jehovah’s calendar.
It’s been there for a long time.
ずっと前からです その日は予定通りに
間違いなくやってきます
It will come on time, at the right time,
at a time that Jehovah
knows to be the best time.
エホバはベストなタイミングで
行動してくださいます
エホバは私たちの親友であり
And isn’t that what we would expect
of our best Friend, Jehovah God;
愛の神であり 時間を守る方であり
the God of love; the Great Timekeeper;
“the King of eternity”?
「永遠の王」だからです
Meditating on the fact
that the day and hour is established
日と時刻が決まっていることを考えると
エホバの日をこれからも辛抱強く待とう
という決意が強まります
helps us renew our resolve
to keep waiting patiently on Jehovah.
でもその日が遅れているように思いますか
But what if the day seems to be delaying?
Interestingly, there at Habakkuk 2:3,
興味深いことに
ハバクク 2:3を見ると
Jehovah himself
brought up the subject of a delay.
エホバご自身がその点を取り上げています
It was Jehovah who said:
エホバはこう言っています
「たとえ遅れるとしても 待ち続けよ」
“Even if it should delay,
keep in expectation of it!”
Well, how could the end come on time
and yet be delayed?
予定通りに来るはずの日が遅れるとは
どういうことでしょうか
Well, consider the situation
back in Habakkuk’s day.
ハバククの時代のことを考えてみましょう
It was about 100 years earlier
その100年ほど前 預言者イザヤは
that the prophet Isaiah had foretold
エホバがバビロンを用いて
裁きを行うと予告しました
that Jehovah would use Babylon
to bring a day of judgment.
Now, if you or I were in Habakkuk’s sandals,
もし私たちがハバククだったら
どう感じたでしょうか
how might we have felt?
From our point of view
enduring that wicked system of things,
当時は大変な時代でした
そういう中で生活していたら
it may have well seemed
that the day of Jehovah was delaying.
エホバの日が遅れていると
感じたかもしれません
いずれにしてもハバククは
And if Habakkuk felt that way,
then Jehovah’s assurances
surely comforted him.
エホバの言葉を聞いて
安心したことでしょう
Again, we noticed that Jehovah
didn’t criticize him
ハバククは 「いつまで」と2回
for asking, How long? How long? twice
「どうして」と2回
「なぜ」と2回尋ねました
and, Why? four times.
でもエホバはハバククを責めたりせず
No.
Jehovah took into consideration
友であるハバククの心の痛みを
理解し 安心させました
the pain of heart of his friend
and then reassured him.
どうなったでしょうか
20年後 エホバの言葉は実現しました
And do you know what happened 20 years later?
Jehovah’s words were fulfilled.
Jerusalem was destroyed in 607 B.C.E.
エルサレムは紀元前607年に
滅ぼされました
So had there really been a delay?
その日は遅れていたのでしょうか
そうではありません
Not at all.
That delay was only a perceived one
その裁きの日は ハバククにとって
in the mind of Habakkuk.
遅れているように思えただけです
Of course, you and I can look back
もちろん私たちは
実際に起きた出来事を知っているので
through the book of history
and see the bigger picture,
俯瞰的に考えることができますが
ハバククは裁きの日がいつ来るかを
正確には知りませんでした
one that Habakkuk
simply could not see fully in his time.
And what do we see now
about that day of judgment
では私たちは 紀元前607年について
どんなことを知っているでしょうか
in 607 B.C.E.?
Well, like a piece
in a very detailed but beautiful puzzle,
ジグソーパズルは最後のピースが
はまると全体像が分かります
the destruction of Jerusalem
came right on time
同様にエルサレムの滅びが
完璧なタイミングで来ることによって
—at the perfect time—
全体像が明らかになりました
because that was a pivotal date
in the fulfillment of other Bible prophecies,
そのタイミングは
他の聖書預言とも関連しています
prophecies that have to do
with our day during the last days.
私たちの時代
今の終わりの時代に関する預言です
So while Habakkuk
may have thought that there was a delay,
ハバククは遅れているように
感じたかもしれませんが
実際はそうではありませんでした
Jehovah knew better.
What’s the reminder
that nourishes our heart this morning?
今日はどんなことを学ぶことが
できたでしょうか
Everything linked to Jehovah’s grand purpose
エホバは時間を守る方です
ご自分が当初考えていた
壮大な事柄を成し遂げるため
has always been and will always be
着々と物事を進めてこられました
in the perfect control
of the Great Timekeeper, Jehovah.
これからもそうされます
今日の朝の崇拝では
ハバククに注目しました
In summary, we could conclude
from our Morning Worship program today
エホバとハバククのやりとりから
大切なことを学べました
that Habakkuk’s experience
teaches us valuable lessons.
1つには エホバはご自分に仕える
人たちの苦しみや心の痛みを
One, Jehovah is not indifferent
to the suffering and the emotional distress
of his servants.
よく分かってくれているということです
So are you in some emotional distress
あなたは心の痛みを抱えていますか
あるいはそういう人を助けていますか
or assisting someone else who is?
Don’t be afraid
to keep pouring out your heart to Jehovah,
遠慮なくエホバに
気持ちを打ち明けてください
何度でも祈れます
仲間にもそうするよう勧めてください
helping others to do so,
even repeatedly if needed.
Like Habakkuk,
wait patiently for the answers,
思いやり深いエホバが与えてくれる答えを
ハバククのように辛抱強く待ちましょう
the reassurance that Jehovah will provide.
Remember this too about the salvation
that Jehovah has foretold:
エホバは私たちをどのように救うと
約束しているでしょうか
His salvation for his people
is not a temporary solution.
エホバの救いは
一時的な解決策ではありません
ばんそうこうを貼るような
ものではないのです
It’s not a bandage on a wound.
His solution will completely resolve
私たちが経験している全ての問題を
any and all trials we may be experiencing.
完全に解決してくださいます
もう二度と悩まされることはありません
Once they’re gone, they’re gone for good.
So how reassuring it is—isn’t it?—to know
うれしいことに 1日を終えるたびに
that today we are one day closer
エホバのカレンダーに記されている日に
また1日近づいたことになります
to the fixed day
that’s on Jehovah’s calendar!
Jehovah’s judgments
by means of his Kingdom will not be late.
エホバが王国によって裁きを下す日は
遅れることはないのです